Hello!
In this episode of Bug Bounty Reports
Explained,
I will show you an incredible
puzzle of low risk bugs
that's chained together, led to an account
takeover on Facebook.com.
The hunter who found it, Yousef Sammouda,
got almost $45,000 for it.
Link to his blog
post is in the description.
Enjoy!
This episode is sponsored by Intigriti.
Intigriti is Europe's
biggest bug bounty platform,
with over 400 programs to hack on.
I hugely appreciate Intigriti for
investing a lot in community enablement.
They create an awesome bug
bytes newsletter, they create monthly XSS
challenges,
they even have a great YouTube channel.
If you are not one of over 50,000 hunters,
check out Intigriti
now using the link from the description.
On Facebook,
you can log in using your password,
but you can also link your account with Gmail
to log in with your Gmail account.
The protocol to do this
is Oauth
and it is widely used across the web.
Very simplified flow of this process
looks like this.
You are on Facebook
and you click log in with Gmail button.
Facebook generates some parameters for you
and redirects you to Gmail.
Then in Gmail, you have to log in.
But usually you are logged in already.
So you only choose the account
and if you only have one account,
Gmail will just flash in front of you
and you will be redirected back
to Facebook.
The parameters, among others,
will contain the code.
Importantly, up until now,
Facebook and Gmail servers
did not communicate with each other.
Only now, when Facebook receives
the code, sends the request
to Gmail server and gives you back the
session token if it's okay.
So this code
is very valuable because it allows you
to exchange it for the session cookie.
So even the attacker would see it,
they could also take over your account.
And across the years, we saw many attacks
that looked more or less like this.
The attacker has to trick the victim
into visiting their website.
The attacker's website sends the victim
into the authentication flow.
But before the original website consumes
the code,
the attacker takes it over
and hijacks user's account.
And this is exactly what we'll try to do
today.
However, in modern web
and on a hardened target like Facebook,
it is not easy.
Definitely much harder
than in the early days of Oauth.
In particular, there are two problems
that we need to solve.
The first one is that the code is one time
use only.
It means if the victim consumes
the code - sends this code to Facebook,
the attacker can't do anything
even if they have the code.
And the other is,
of course, leaking the code somehow.
So to prevent the code
from being used by the victim,
we need to stop this flow somewhere
between Gmail and Facebook.
On Facebook,
If you make too many requests,
your account will enter a state
where you need to fill in the CAPTCHA.
I would call it the captcha state.
Whatever you will try to do on Facebook,
you will be shown this window.
And it is a very good candidate
to solve the first problem
because if the victim's account will be in
the lockout state, in the captcha state,
after they finish the authentication flow,
they won't use the code.
And importantly, the code will be
in the URL of the website,
giving us some chance to leak it.
But how do
we force the victim's account
into the CAPTCHA state?
The answer to that is that we don't.
Instead, we will introduce
the CAPTCHA state into our own account.
And then we'll use two bugs
to log out the victim from their account
using one CSRF and then log in the victim
into our account using another CSRF.
These two bugs, even though they are very low
risk by themselves, chained together here
will allow us to move
the victim's Facebook
into the captcha state.
Now, you might be asking yourself,
how do we take over a victim's account
if they are logged in to our account?
But the thing is that
in case of this attack,
Facebook
won't actually take part in this process.
We are interested in Gmail
generating the code
and taking over this code, which
will allow us to take over the account.
So it doesn't matter what account is
the victim logged in on Facebook.com.
So we are able to log out the victim
from their account,
log in them to our account
which is in the captcha state.
We can send them
into the authentication flow
and we make sure
that they come back to Facebook,
they don't consume the code
and the code is in the URL.
Now the question is how to leak this code
from this URL.
Normally,
if you want to add a CAPTCHA functionality
from a third party
provider to your website,
you have to import their scripts
on your website.
It requires some level of trust
and to be even more secure,
Facebook didn't host this window, this iframe, on Facebook.com domain,
but on their sandbox domain.
Sandbox
domains often improve security of websites
because even though Facebook owns
these two domains,
browsers don't know about it
and they treat them like they would be
completely different ones.
They have different cookies,
different storage, different everything.
They just have one communication
channel to establish
if the captcha was filled in or not.
But for the sandbox to be an improvement
of security of the website,
it can't be used in too many contexts.
But in this case it was
because it was also used
on the testing website
when the developers can see
how a particular website
will look inside the Facebook mobile app.
And this allowed them to upload
HTML files,
which would be stored
on the same sandbox domain.
And even though the sandbox
domain is separate from Facebook.com,
the sandbox domains
can somehow communicate with each other
because they are the same origin.
And this is the last piece of our puzzle.
Now let's combine them all together
to see the whole exploit.
Usually, in case of a client side attack,
you create your own website
and you have to trick the victim
into visiting, for example, attacker.com
domain.
In this case, we'll instead
host the whole exploit
on the Facebook sandbox domain
because it will be helpful later.
Before we attack
the victim, we have to force our account
into the captcha state.
Then, when the victim visits our exploit,
first, we have to log them out
from their account using the CSRF.
Then, we have to log them into our account
using another CSRF.
Then, we have this URL.
Importantly, we open this in a new tab and
we save the reference to that window.
If the victim is already logged
in, in Gmail, Gmail
just flashes in front of them
and redirects back to Facebook.
Facebook is in the captcha state,
which means they land on the captcha
screen and importantly, the URL with
the code is inside the iframe's address.
Now from the original window,
we have the reference
to the newly opened window.
These two are now in separate domains
because our website is on the sandbox
domain and the victim is now
on the Facebook.com domain.
So we only have limited access
to properties from Facebook.com.
However, those limited
properties include the list of frames
on that website.
And we know that the first iframe,
the ifame with the index zero,
is the captcha window,
which is also on the sandbox domain.
And all of a sudden, our exploit website
and the iframe
with the sensitive code in the address
are on the same origin, meaning
they can communicate with each other.
And our exploit website has access
to the address of the iframe,
which contains the code.
We now send the code to our server
and we need a script to exchange this code
for a victim's session cookie,
taking over their account.
So the bug allowed to take over
any Facebook
account
of someone that uses Gmail to log in.
The reward for it was almost $45,000.
Of course, the bug is already fixed.
Check out this
playlist to see two more account
takeovers on Facebook
that were rewarded $25k and $55k.
And if you enjoyed this video
leave a like and subscribe to the channel.
For now,
thank you for watching and goodbye!